This is my kitchen table and it's also
my filing system.
Over much of the past three decades,
I've been an investor the highest
calling of mankind I've often thought
was private equity.
And then I started interviewing.
Oh, I watch your interview interviews,
Coach.
I know how to do it.
I've learned in doing my interviews how
leaders make it to the top.
I asked him how much he wanted.
He said to 50.
I said, Fine.
I didn't negotiate with him.
I didn't know due diligence to have
something I'd like to sell and how they
stay there.
You don't feel inadequate now because
being only the second wealthiest man in
the world, is that right?
One of the largest and most successful
companies in India is the Mahindra
Group, a family owned conglomerate.
I had a chance to sit down with the
first person in 80 years to run that
company who is not a member of the
family, a Nisha.
I sat down with him to talk about how
he's taking Mahindra into a different
route, not only as an exporter to the
United States and other countries, but
also enhancing what it's doing in India.
So for those people that don't know that
much about India, what is the Mahindra
Group and what does it actually make
today with the Mahindra Group has been
around for eight years now.
We operate in more than 20 industries in
70% of India's GDP.
We make SUVs.
We are the largest maker of SUVs in
India.
Light commercial vehicles, electric
three wheelers.
We are the largest tractor maker in
India.
Farm equipment.
And not just in India, but globally.
We are the largest maker of tractors
from a volume standpoint.
We are in financial services, IT
services.
We are the largest in logistics because
the largest renewable invit in India.
In hospitality, in real estate and a
number of other areas.
So when was Mahindra Group started?
1945.
And this came together with three
founders, the Mindoro Brothers and
Ghulam Mohamad.
When India and Pakistan partitioned
column one would want to be the first
finance minister of Pakistan.
And that's when the two Mindoro brothers
took it forward as my reminder.
And today, what percentage of your sales
are in India and what percentage are
outside India?
We have about 70% in India and 30%
outside.
As you look at India, is India in
reasonably good shape financially and
the economy is doing reasonably well?
India is in a very good shape and
we strongly feel that India will grow 8
to 10% a year for the next 20 years.
There are three key drivers of that.
One is the demographics.
India is the youngest country by far.
The average age of the median age is
28.8 years as compared to the late
thirties for China and the US, Japan
closer to the late forties.
And second is the reforms.
The government has really put in a
number of reforms in place over the past
few years.
Third is infrastructure, both the
physical infrastructure.
We are building nearly 40 miles of roads
per day for the last ten years.
We've got one airport coming up per
month for the last ten years.
We've got very strong digital
infrastructure in place as well, which
is, I would say, among the best in the
world.
So I look at all of these things.
India, which has grown six and a half
percent a year for the last 30 years, is
going to make that jump to 8 to 10%,
become the third largest economy by 2030
and by 2047.
The forecast for India or the goal for
India is to be at 32 trillion.
From a GDP standpoint, India is the most
populous country in the world.
It is.
How many people?
1.4.
5 billion.
It is the in terms of the economy today
in the world, it's in the top ten.
In terms of GDP.
Today it's number four and going towards
number three.
Would you say that India has some
challenges with the United States?
Because as we talk, the United States
seems to have imposed or at least says
it's going to impose a tariff of 50% on
Indian products.
And I assume that's not going to be
helpful to you.
That will not be helpful.
But from an economy standpoint, it won't
have as much of an impact because India
is largely a consumption led economy.
However, this is one that is concerning
because India and the US have had a very
strong relationship and has been getting
even stronger over the last few years.
And therefore
we are puzzled, to say the least at this
point in time, and we hope that things
will get much better as we go forward.
How much of your time do you have to
spend outside of India?
I'd say about 30 to 40% because for us
we're looking at the world as a market
as well as potential for partnerships
that can help us grow our India
business.
Now, if the United States imposes a 50%
tariff on things coming in from India,
that can't be helpful.
So how do you deal with that?
That clearly will not be helpful, but we
see huge opportunity, David.
It's not just about goods and services.
So India and the US are roughly equal
from services imported and exported on
goods.
There is a deficit from a US
perspective, but the real opportunity is
for US companies to bring the technology
to India to be able to do a lot more for
Indian companies to invest in the US and
be able to bring its products here,
which is what we are planning to do, and
that we feel will come out as time goes
on and will get to a much stronger place
for both countries.
So it's the case that as we talk over
the weekend, we saw a picture of Mr.
Modi and President Xi and President
Putin kind of acting like their soul
brothers.
Is that a surprise that India and China
would be so close after the border
disputes and the problems they've had?
Or do you think this is a natural
evolution?
I feel that India is very close to the
US and has been for many years.
India also has always been non-aligned
and has believed that the world is one
family.
What should they be?
Could become is a phrase that's used.
In India.
So while I can't comment on the politics
as much, what I can say is that from
everything that I've seen growing up,
from living in the US for 14 years as
well, that the India US relationship has
been really very strong and we've gone
through hiccups in the past.
We had that at the time of the nuclear
tests that India did in 1998 and became
much stronger after that.
And we hope that this again is a hiccup
that will get past and really establish
a very strong relationship between the
two countries which who are natural
allies.
Now, recently, President Trump said he
helped to arbitrate a dispute between
India and Pakistan, for which he has
said maybe he should get the Nobel Peace
Prize.
Mr.
Modi has said, well, it really wasn't
quite that way.
Do you know enough about that to say
what actually happened?
Is India and Pakistan, are they in
dispute right now?
So I don't know about what happened
there, so I can't quite comment on that
part.
But India is really focused on driving
economic growth.
That's the agenda the president has laid
out and ambition.
The prime minister has laid out a very
ambitious plan around the exit path or a
develop India, and that is a plan for
1944, getting to 2047 with a $32
trillion economy.
Now, talk about agricultural product.
You make what kind of agricultural
equipment?
We make tractors and other farm
equipment as well.
Tractors.
We are the largest in India with a 45%
market share and the largest automaker
by volume globally.
Is that for use in India or outside?
In India and outside, we've got a
business in the US, which is the third
largest tractor maker in the US for
smaller tractors, which is less than a
hundred, and you manufacture them in
India or the United States.
We get gets to the US and assemble them
here.
So we have an assembly factory in Texas
and that's where we put them.
What other businesses are you around?
You have automobiles, you've got,
say, farm equipment.
What else are you in?
I.T.
services.
It's a large business for us.
And I.t.
Services makes up the majority of our
employees in the US, along with a
tractor business.
Then we have financial services.
We are the largest financial services
provider for rural India.
We've got hospitality, we've got 100
resorts in India, Real estate logistics.
We are the largest logistics company in
India as well.
It takes a lot of expertise to do
automobiles.
I like farm equipment, hotels and isn't
that a lot of different skill sets you
need to have?
You need to have the skill set of
getting good people and making sure that
there's a right process in place for
capital allocation, the right process
for strategic thought and growth, and
making sure that
there's empowerment for all leaders,
because that's the only way that this
business works.
And you see a lot of Americans now
coming to invest in India.
I know my own company now, investors a
lot that's a lot in India, but are a lot
of other people doing that as well?
We see tremendous interest in India, and
that's the reason I spend a lot of time
in various geographies meeting with
various companies who want to come to
India and looking for partnerships with
them and looking for that technology to
be adopted in the Indian market.
If I wanted to invest in India, would
you say it's a good place in which to
invest as a financial investor, a
country that's growing 8 to 10% a year
for the next 20 years would be a
fantastic place.
That's the choice that we are making as
well.
But we're investing not only in India
but also in a few other parts of the
world.
The US being a specific area.
If I'm an American company and I want to
invest in Asia,
why would I want to invest in India over
China without getting you banned from
going back to China?
Why would somebody want to invest in
India over China?
India has a lot of similarities to the
US.
It's a democracy.
It has rule of law, it's a capitalist
society.
And that's what a number of companies
are seeing now.
Many companies will look at a back up
option for China as well.
And some companies I know are looking at
India as a primary option going forward.
Also, the biggest country in the world,
population wise was China, and now it's
India.
And China also has a very elderly
population, relatively speaking,
compared to India.
Why are they so different?
India has evolved over time and India
has realized that
it has to drive capitalism because that
is one way where everyone will get
wealthier.
And that's been a big benefit for India.
It also never had birth control in any
form and or rather in the form that
China did, which was a one child policy.
And that I think is impacting China to
an extent right now with India not
having had that has a natural population
growth that we are seeing today.
Now, there are many companies in Silicon
Valley that are run by people of Indian
background.
I think something like a third of the
companies in Silicon Valley are run by
people who came from India, either this
generation or.
Previous generation.
So why is that?
Why are so many talented people from
India leaving India and going to Silicon
Valley?
We have a lot of talented people in
India as well.
So it is just a function of the
opportunities that folks get.
It's also a great learning ground in the
US.
I learnt a tremendous amount in the US
and that's something that benefits me as
we are building a company that really is
a global company at this point.
Historically, India wasn't, as I would
say, hospitable to capitalism as maybe
people wouldn't United States would have
liked.
I think Indira Gandhi, when she was the
head of India, probably was leaning more
towards things that were not pro
capitalism.
How has that changed in recent years
under Mr.
Modi?
That has changed dramatically and that
is evident in the reforms that have been
done in the mindset.
The government is very focused on ease
of doing business.
It has it is pushing companies to get
larger.
For us, we have grown our market cap 12
times in the last five years
and that really is a function of the
opportunities that we see in India
today.
Let's talk about your own background for
a moment.
So where were you born?
In Mumbai.
Mumbai.
And were you educated there as a young
boy?
I was.
I did my early schooling in Mumbai.
I went to one of the top institutes in
India for an MBA.
The I am and the board then worked with
Citibank in Mumbai for a couple of years
and came to the US for a Ph.D.
at Carnegie Mellon and continued to stay
in the US for 14 years before going back
to India.
What did your parents do?
My father and mother were both graduates
from my mother, but my father spent
most of his life with Pfizer in India
and then founded the Indian
Pharmaceutical Association and really
helped Indian pharmaceutical companies
come up to the level where they are
today.
And my mother was an entrepreneur in the
late sixties and early seventies.
Do you have siblings, a younger sister
who also was in the US for 20 years and
is back in India now?
So you grew up in India.
Get your education there.
Why did you decide to come to the United
States to get a Ph.D.
from Carnegie Mellon?
One of my aspirations was to be the CEO
of a US company in India, and to do
that, I felt I needed to understand the
US better get a US degree, and that was
a reason to come to the US.
And what was your PhD in corporate
governance?
It was within the accounting department,
but my advisor was very keen on
corporate governance and that is a focus
on my Ph.D..
So after you got your Ph.D., Sam,
rushing back to India, or did you stay
in the United States for a while?
I stayed in the US, got a job with Bain
in Boston, was there for three years,
and then with G.E.
Capital for a long time in the US and
then went back to India with G.E.
Capital as a CEO in India.
So you're working for GE Capital at that
time.
I assume Jack Welch or somebody like
that was running G.E.
Jeff Immelt had just taken over from
Jack and G Capital was at that point
doing very well.
So somebody poach you, somebody call you
up and say, forget GE Capital.
You should work for an Indian company.
So a mentor of mine from Bain, in fact,
reached out and introduced me to Anand
Mahindra, and I had a great meeting with
him and in fact continued meeting him
for a couple of years.
Almost every month we would meet.
And Anand wanted me to come and join the
Mindray group, and I'm very glad I did
that.
What year was that that you joined the
group?
2014 Regarding 1214, what was your
initial job?
There was head of group strategy and it
was a job that I held for five years
before being appointed in this role.
So you became the CEO in 2021?
That's correct.
And this is the first time that the
Mahindra Group had ever had a non
Mahindra family member run the company.
That's right.
So then you join the company.
Do you ever think that would ever
happen?
When I joined, I joined with the
objective of making a significant
difference, and the group was the most
respected group in India and one where
there was a level of empowerment for all
its leaders.
That is what an that had set up at that
point.
And while there was a view that, look,
there is a possibility of a Group C
role, it wasn't known at that point in
time and that evolved as I went on
there.
So there's a story that I read about
which said that when you were working
your way up to become the CEO, but no
guarantees you were going to be the CEO,
you disagreed with Mr.
Mahindra on the matter and you took it
to the board and you explained to the
board while he was wrong and you were
right and the board sided with you,
didn't you think that was going to be
the end of your career when you did
that?
So what happened actually was I was
sitting with Mr.
Mandara and one of my colleagues came in
to show what was being presented to the
board the next day, and Mr.
Windsor, in his usual manner, said, What
do you think?
So I looked at that and said, I wouldn't
do this for these reasons.
And that is the level of empowerment and
openness that Mr.
Mindray had fostered in the group.
When he said that, I'm going to call you
to the board meeting tomorrow and I'm
going to ask you the same question as I
asked you today, and please give them
the same answer that you gave me today.
And that then transpired into the
response.
He was setting you up for failure or
something by having the board vote you
down or something or not.
No, I knew him very well by then because
I had met him, as I said, every month
for a couple of years before I came to
the group.
And to me that was one of the biggest
attractors for me because it was a group
where it was truly very open.
It was, Say what you want to say as long
as it's good for the company.
And that company first aspect was very
much a factor there.
So you you overcame that or maybe that
wasn't a problem to overcome.
And in 2021, you became the head of the
company that the group's CEO, was Mr.
Mahindra still around?
He is, and I reached out to him on a
very regular basis for guidance to tell
you you're not doing this right or
you're not doing that right, or we have
a great relationship where he empowers
as much as he can.
And I pull on his guidance as much as I
can.
So.
And then a hundred families still own a
large part of the company.
Yes, they still own what they have over
time, which is close to about 20%.
But how many and total employees do you
have in the entire Mahindra Group?
320,000.
A lot of people to be taking care of.
That is a lot of people.
And how many in the United States are
close to 10,000?
Other than India, where do you have your
most employees after outside of India?
Is it the United States or some other?
It is the United States.
What's the biggest problem you have now
as a CEO of a company navigating all the
challenges that the world is throwing up
because that keeps happening on a
regular basis.
In your own case, what do you do on the
outside when you're not running
Mahindra?
Do you have any time for hobbies,
philanthropy, sports?
What do you do?
Are you a big cricket player or cricket
watcher?
Sports Spending time with family,
reading and doing a lot on
the purpose front.
And I'll start with that because my
interest is really a purpose led
company.
So we are purpose led and performance
driven, as we call it, but we start with
purpose.
We have focused on education for young
girls in India and we've educated close
to a million girls in India so far.
We've set a target to do a million a
year.
We are at this point about one fourth
the target, but in the next two or three
years, we should be able to get to our
target.
We are also focusing on empowering women
to find jobs and making them financially
independent.
And they are.
Again, our target is a million a year.
The Gates Foundation is partnering with
us on this, and we are, again at this
point about one fourth the target, but
we will get there soon.
And these are some of the activities
that really make a difference to India
overall.
So when we say purpose led
DNA actually comes from our founders,
they talked about dignity of labour, but
neither caste nor creed nor color shall
come in the way of a meritocracy.
But that was what they truly believed,
that the company has to do well for
society, for communities
to.
So if somebody is watching and you
wanted to say to them, here's what you
need to know in one paragraph about
Mahindra.
And one paragraph, what you need to know
about India mantra is a purpose led,
performance driven company.
Our purpose is a Rice philosophy, which
is to drive positive change in the lives
of our communities to enable them to
rise
from a performance standpoint.
We are the best performing stock in the
nifty50 since 2002.
So even though our market cap has grown
12 weeks in the last five years, it's
been a long journey where we've been at
the top of performance in India.
We operate in 20 industries across 70%
of India's GDP and we are building a
global company and hopefully one that
will be a very large company in the US
as well.
India is poised to be at a very rapid
growth over the next 20 years.
We expect that growth to be 8 to 10%.
The foundation for that growth has been
built.
It's a consumption driven economy.
And therefore, despite all the
challenges in the world, we feel that
India will grow at that pace.
India will be the third largest economy
by 2030.
It's a capitalist economy driven by rule
of law, with a government today that is
very focused on ease of business, on
ensuring that companies can succeed in
India and therefore is a very good
destination for companies.
Why should somebody as a tourist want to
go to India?
What are you what's the best thing to
see in India?
Why should somebody go for a week to
India as a tourist?
India has some amazing destinations and
India is now opening up tourism in
various forms.
There are multiple things to see in
different parts of the country.
From the Taj Mahal in Agra to the
deserts of Rajasthan to the greenery in
Kerala.
You've got a large number of things in
India that that are worth looking at.
Now, amazingly, when you go back in
history, it appears that Britain ruled
India with only 20,000 soldiers in the
entire country.
India had a population, maybe then of a
billion people.
How did India allow Britain, this small
country way in the North Sea, to control
India for so long?
How did that happen?
India has always been a country that has
stood for peace and therefore even the
resistance to the British was with
non-violence, and that is what Gandhi
led.
So that has been one of the hallmarks of
India over centuries.
And so how old are you now?
55.
Is there a retirement age that people
have normally in India?
Or you can go for as long as you want to
go?
We have a 65 retirement age, so.
So you're going to do this presumably
for another ten years?
At this point, I love it.
And hopefully I will continue loving it
for the next ten years.
And you have the responsibility of
grooming your successor as well, or
Mahindra that might come back.
That is unknown.
Most likely it will be someone from
the team or professional successor.
And there will be various folks that I
will groom over the next ten years and
present options to the board for the
water decide at that point.
Many companies that succeed have a
founder who might have a certain
philosophy and certain set of
principles.
Did the Mahindra family, when it
started, have a certain principles that
they imbued in Mahindra and you still
live with those principles If it was the
case that they have those principles.
So when we say purpose led, a DNA
actually comes from our founders.
When they founded the company in 1945 to
place an advertisement in The Times of
India that talked about the principles
under which the company was born.
They talked about dignity of labour, but
neither caste nor creed nor colour shall
come in the way of a meritocracy, but
opposing anti social trends.
Today, it would read like an ESG
manifesto, but that was what it truly
believed that the company has to do well
for society, for communities.
And therefore we say we are purpose led
because that is our DNA
to.